<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon touching the divine right and due observation of the Lords day Preached before the Lord Deputy, and the Lords Spiritual &amp; Temporal of the kingdom of Ireland; in time of Parliament. At Christ-Church Dublin. On Sunday the 6th. of October, 1695. With a preface humbly address'd to the whole body of English Protestants: especially those inhabiting the kingdom of Ireland. By Edward Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross.</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1520A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96264)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2320:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon touching the divine right and due observation of the Lords day Preached before the Lord Deputy, and the Lords Spiritual &amp; Temporal of the kingdom of Ireland; in time of Parliament. At Christ-Church Dublin. On Sunday the 6th. of October, 1695. With a preface humbly address'd to the whole body of English Protestants: especially those inhabiting the kingdom of Ireland. By Edward Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross.</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], xx, 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Joseph Ray in Essex-street, and are to be sold by John North bookseller in Skinner-row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Edward Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross = Edward Wettenhall.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152772:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152772:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Touching the DIVINE RIGHT AND DUE OBSERVATION OF THE LORDS DAY.</p>
            <p>Preached before the LORD DEPUTY, and the Lords SPIRITUAL &amp; TEMPORAL of the Kingdom of IRELAND; In time of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. At Chriſt-Church <hi>Dublin.</hi> On <hi>Sunday</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>With a PREFACE humbly addreſs'd to the whole Body of Engliſh Proteſtants: Eſpecially thoſe inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the Kingdom of <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDWARD <hi>Lord Bishop of</hi> Cork <hi>and</hi> Roſs.</p>
            <p>DUBLIN: Printed by Joſeph Ray in Eſſex-ſtreet, and are to be ſold by John North Bookſeller in Skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-row, 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152772:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:152772:2"/>
            <head>A PREFACE to the enſuing SERMON. Humbly Addreſs'd To the Whole Body of <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants:</hi> Eſpecially thoſe inhabiting the Kingdom of <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Have long grieved to ſee the <hi>Sacredneſs of the Lords Day</hi> run ſo <hi>low,</hi> as too plainly it appears to do, in the opinion of Multitudes, who profeſs themſelves of the <hi>Reformed Church of Ireland;</hi> From the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> I never expected better, ſince I came to know them: They will <hi>never have venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for any thing which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> account <hi>ſacred;</hi> as witneſs their conſtant treatment of our <hi>Bibles.</hi> Nor do I apprehend any <hi>poſſibility</hi> of <hi>Reforming</hi> them, either in this or any other of their Ill Principles and practices, while they have a ſett of ſuch Managers as their <hi>preſent Prieſts</hi> allowed them: and thoſe too, with ſo <hi>abſolute a Dominion</hi> over them, as is uſual in that Church.</p>
            <p>But for men, that own the name of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and glory to be thought <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> for theſe I ſay, openly to eſpouſe the calumny of <hi>Figmentum Anglicanum,</hi> in caſe of a <hi>Divine right</hi> for the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and purſuant hereto in their <hi>Practice</hi> perfectly to <hi>fall in with Papiſts,</hi> laying aſide all <hi>Afternoon worſhip</hi> on the Lords Day, as is done now in very many
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:152772:3"/> 
               <hi>Country Pariſhes</hi> in this Kingdom, and onely in the <hi>Morning</hi> ſometimes, for faſhion-ſake to <hi>come to Church,</hi> as the others do to their <hi>Maſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>houſes,</hi> is a ſad demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that either they <hi>never</hi> were <hi>true Proteſtants</hi> (becauſe not underſtanding, or not receiving and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Doctrine, Laws and Worſhip of the Church, whereof they profeſs themſelves Members) or that they have now moſt <hi>deplorably degenerated</hi> and fallen off from its conſtitution.</p>
            <p>There is yet a farther and <hi>more abominable neglect,</hi> than that, which I have complained of, (and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no doubt from the ſame Principle, that is mean and common thoughts of the Lords Day) perhaps not ſo conſtant as the other, but very common in <hi>Country-Cures,</hi> namely that they are <hi>not ſupplyed</hi> any otherwiſe but <hi>once a fortnight,</hi> or in ſome places once in <hi>three weeks;</hi> yea even where the revenues of the place, either of it ſelf, or by unions, would well pay a Curate reſident, and conſtantly attendant.</p>
            <p>With an eye at <hi>redreſſing</hi> theſe ſo <hi>inſufferable and unchriſtian evils,</hi> I firſt <hi>delivered</hi> in a great audience, and now <hi>publiſh</hi> to the World the <hi>enſuing diſcourſe.</hi> In which I ſtruck at the root, the Principle before taxed; and have <hi>laid together,</hi> in the cleareſt light, briefeſt compaſs, and moſt Natural order (as neer as I could comprehend) all the <hi>beſt Evidences,</hi> I remember produced, <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plea for the Divine right</hi> of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and the true <hi>Chriſtian way</hi> of <hi>hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> it. Which latter point I have ſtated, I hope; ſo as to <hi>conduct</hi> all, who will <hi>hear,</hi> into truly Holy practice; but not to <hi>burden</hi> or <hi>intangle</hi> the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of any, who will <hi>conſider.</hi> And all along, as <hi>Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
               <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:152772:3"/> 
               <hi>ad homines,</hi> and a Plea which I had great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in, I have urged ſincerely, what I take to be the <hi>Doctrine of the Church of England,</hi> in this matter. It is not to be expected that in ſo ſhort a piece, all ſhould be ſaid in ſuch manner as is neceſſary to <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>Exceptions</hi> or <hi>anſwer the Cavils</hi> of many: I accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it therefore neceſſary, here to add a few things, as well for the one purpoſe as the other.</p>
            <p>I have aſſerted a Divine right to the Lords Day. Now a <hi>Divine Right</hi> may ariſe from a <hi>Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Immediate</hi> or <hi>Mediate:</hi> And again, either of theſe may be <hi>expreſs</hi> or <hi>virtual.</hi> There are not wanting Authors, of great Name, who have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the <hi>Lords day</hi> to have been appointed, for the day of publick Chriſtian Worſhip, by our <hi>Lords own mouth,</hi> at ſome of his Apparitions, and in ſome of his Diſcourſes to his Diſciples, in the <hi>interval</hi> of his <hi>Reſurection</hi> and <hi>Aſcention.</hi> If ſo, then would there be a <hi>Divine Right by immediate expreſs Inſtitutior.</hi> But I will frankly acknowledg this (although not at all unlikely, but rather of the higheſt probability, yet) to have been advanced, in my judgment, with better Intention than Evidence. I have therefore mainly, as to Authority immediate from our Lord himſelf, inſiſted upon his <hi>own practice,</hi> by his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent preſence at, and ſolemn meeting in, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of his Diſciples and faithful followers, on that day; And when he appeared no more, ſending in their Aſſembly on that day, the Holy Ghoſt upon them all; which I aver to be <hi>Virtual Inſtitution:</hi> And if an Inſtitution, there is no queſtion at all, of
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:152772:4"/> it's being <hi>immediately Divine.</hi> Then in purſuance hereof, I inſiſt alſo on the <hi>continued practice</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> from the very day of our Lords Reſurrection, as far as is Recorded, ſolemnly aſſembling, ſtill on that day (which can hardly be conceived without ſome private directions ſuggeſted from himſelf) and their <hi>giving order in the Churches</hi> (eſpecially of the <hi>Gentiles)</hi> which they planted for the publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies to be made hereon. Their <hi>practice</hi> I aver to be a <hi>continuance of a virtual Divine Inſtitution,</hi> and their <hi>Orders given,</hi> an <hi>expreſs Divine Inſtitution,</hi> but both indeed <hi>Mediate.</hi> And if there be any of our Church who are not willing to allow theſe, and eſpecially the <hi>Apoſtles practice and orders,</hi> to be ſufficient grounds of a <hi>Divine Right,</hi> I deſire, that they will not herein be <hi>too peremptory,</hi> leaſt they be found <hi>leſs conſtant</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; particularly, in denying that to be a Divine Right in caſe of the Lords day, which they not onely admit but plead as a Divine Right, in other caſes, to ſome of them perhaps of more comfortable impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; ſuppoſe Epiſcopacy and Church-Rights.</p>
            <p>As to ſtyling the Lords day a <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath</hi> (which I have not done, but after our Church) I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg it can be called ſo only (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and <hi>not ſtrictly.</hi> THE <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly &amp; eminently, is that, which <hi>remains to the people of God.</hi> Heb. iv. 9. <hi>A Chriſtian Sabbath,</hi> I conceive, it may with much more propriety be called. For if it be a Sabbath at all (or a day of Reſt ordinarily from ſervile labour) it muſt be acknowledged a Chriſtian Sabbath: <hi>Jewiſh, Turkiſh,</hi> or <hi>Heathen</hi> we are ſure
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:152772:4"/> it is not. And for giving it the Name <hi>Sabbath,</hi> though I confeſs the frequency of this ſtyle is more Novel, and peculiar to ſome People, yet it is plain, by our <hi>Homilies,</hi> that <hi>Our Reformers</hi> did uſe it. And I am ſure <hi>Origen</hi> ſo ſtyles it, and if I am not miſtaken another of the Fathers alſo, whom I name not for fear of errour; the beſt part of my books having been ſtrangers to my Eyes, now above ſeven years: for which reaſon I have forborn to cite parricularly moſt of the Authorities I have alledged as I paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. But if need be I promiſe ſacredly particular citations in a new Edition, when God ſhall reſtore my books to me. I alledge, what I do now, moſtly out of <hi>Excerpta,</hi> taken many years ago by my ſelf, but not with connexions and references ſo particular, as I can fully truſt to. But to Return. That which makes many perſons of ſound and good Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhy of this name Sabbath <hi>under Chriſtianity,</hi> is I conceive, for that they, who uſe it moſt, ſeem under this ſtyle to endeavour the introducing a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daical Yoke,</hi> and entiteling the <hi>Lords day,</hi> to all the <hi>Sabbatical ſtrictneſſes or ſeverities</hi> of the bodily Reſt, impoſed on the old people, by the letter of the fourth Commandment, and the Precepts appendant to it, in the Law. As to <hi>Duration of time,</hi> they would oblige all Chriſtian people to a <hi>Natural</hi> day of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four hours, from Even to Even, or from twelve of the Clock Midnight to twelve of the Clock Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; in all which ſpace, they would bear us in hand, nothing is to be done, which was not lawful for the Jews to have done on their Sabbath. Nay indeed
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:152772:5"/> as to the <hi>ſtrictneſs of the Reſt,</hi> diverſe Liberties allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (becauſe not forbidden) the Jews, are by theſe teachers, upon the pretence of a <hi>Sabbath Spiritual</hi> as well as Corporal, ſaid to be forbidden Chriſtian people; even by the <hi>letter of the fourth Commandment.</hi> And thus, intolerable burthens, and inextricable ſnares, the particulars of which would require a volume to ſet down, are prepared for us. As to all which, I conceive, if People would duely heed, no more need to be ſaid, for the diſentangling Conſcience, from the ſcruples theſe men have injected, than that true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtolical Canon, Acts xv. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt, and to us, to lay no greater burden upon you than theſe neceſſary things; That ye abſtain from meats offered to Idols, and from bloud, and from things ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and from fornication:</hi> Amongſt which <hi>neceſſary things,</hi> there is <hi>no Syllable</hi> importing any of the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batical Rites.</hi> Nor can it be ſaid, the Reaſon of ſuch ſilence was, the ſenſe the world had of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable Obligation of the fourth Command; for the Obligation of the ſixth, and ſeventh Commandments muſt be acknowledged as immutable; yet is there mention here of <hi>Fornication,</hi> and of <hi>Blood,</hi> in the very Conciliary Decree. I do conclude therefore, as well from hence, as from <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> ii. (urged in the diſcourſe) that all the <hi>Ceremonial part</hi> of the <hi>fourth Command,</hi> with the appendant Laws, are truely ceaſed; <hi>nailed to the Croſs</hi> of Chriſt, and by it taken away; which is amply ſufficient for the ſetting Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience at liberty. But I muſt together conclude that the <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Spiritual part</hi> of that <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:152772:5"/> are <hi>no whit</hi> at all <hi>infringed.</hi> The natural part was and is nothing but immutable and <hi>Eternal Equity.</hi> That <hi>God ſhould have a due proportion of our time;</hi> And that not ſo much privately, by ſecret Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our own (though that be neceſſary alſo) as by <hi>a publick ſeparating it,</hi> or cutting it off, from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Employments, to publick ſacred Offices. Thus much of a Sabbath I inſiſt on to be <hi>perpetually, and naturally Moral,</hi> from <hi>Paradiſe in Eden,</hi> to <hi>Paradiſe in a better World.</hi> And as to the <hi>Spiritual part</hi> of the Command, that certainly is ſo far from being abated by the Goſpel-Oeconomy, that it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet higher. There is none deny the <hi>Chriſtian is bound to the Spiritual Reſt:</hi> onely ſome tell us, and that not without Reaſon, that this is our Duty, <hi>for our whole life,</hi> and not for one day in the week onely.</p>
            <p>I embrace with all my heart this Doctrine, of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian peoples being obliged to endeavour, their whole life may be a Spiritual Sabbath, a Reſt from Sin, Carnality Voluptuouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I onely deſire we may hold to it. Let all thoſe therefore, who hold this Doctrine pardon me, if I adventure (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Conceſſions, <hi>Minus aequo petere, ut aequum feram)</hi> to intreat them, and all Chriſtian People, but to keep the <hi>Lords day</hi> as <hi>ſuch a Spiritual Reſt.</hi> In plain terms, I would deſire no more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the keeping Holy the Lords day, than that the <hi>Chriſtians of the preſent Age,</hi> would in private <hi>keep the Lords day as perfectly a Spiritual Sabbath,</hi> as the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians did every day in the week:</hi>
               <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:152772:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> onely with this <hi>Addition;</hi> That what <hi>publick Offices</hi> the Primitive Chriſtians obſerved conſtantly on <hi>each Lords day,</hi> may alſo be <hi>obſerved</hi> thereon by us at preſent; and <hi>what Liberties</hi> they <hi>forbore always, may be forborn on this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The point of controverſy falls mainly on <hi>private</hi> or <hi>Family-duties.</hi> Theſe ſome men cannot endure that all Chriſtian People ſhould be obliged to: And for the ſhifting off the neceſſity of theſe, and ſetting the ordinary people free to <hi>Games and Sports</hi> on the <hi>Lords Day-afternoon,</hi> diverſe Laborious, and ſome truely not unlearned Books, have been written. Wherein I muſt confeſs I cannot but wonder to ſee Proteſtant Doctors hunt for, and greedily ſnap thoſe Nice diſtinctions, in uſe with the Popiſh Schools, for the defence of the corruptions of their Church, and gravely apply them for the deciſion of Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience againſt their Proteſtant Brethren: I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lanch forth into particulars of Controverſy, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, purſuant to what I now deſired, onely lay down <hi>two concluſions,</hi> which I ſuppoſe muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves, by their own <hi>intrinſick Evidence,</hi> without Controverſy, to the conſcience of all who underſtand and will conſider them. 1. None who call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may, in this Age make ſuch <hi>Liberties, Sports, Games</hi> and <hi>Recreations,</hi> as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians allowed</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on <hi>any days,</hi> to be their <hi>ordinary divertiſments on the Lords Day.</hi> And if ſo, I am ſure <hi>Cards, Dice, Tables,</hi> &amp;c. within doors; <hi>Dancing, Pipeing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells,</hi> &amp;c. without doors, muſt all be laid aſide.
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:152772:6"/> For none can ſhew, the Antient Chriſtians uſed theſe any daies. On the contrary many Canons of the antient Councils ſeverelly condemn them at all times; eſpecially to ſome Perſons. And if there ſhould be any of our <hi>Clergy,</hi> who plead for thoſe <hi>within-door Games</hi> mentioned, they will do well to conſult the XLII. <hi>Iriſh Canon,</hi> and the <hi>Old Injunctions</hi> in the Reformation of <hi>King Edward</hi> and <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> whence moſt probably the Compilers of our Canons more immediatly took thoſe parts of them, and whence I hope they may be ſatisfied. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: I ſay <hi>2dly.</hi> In all <hi>doubtful caſes,</hi> it is ſtill the beſt to take the <hi>ſafer ſide,</hi> and that, which in it ſelf cannot be ſinful, but is Pious and commendable. Now certainly, upon the Lords day, <hi>preparing</hi> our ſelves for our <hi>publick Devotions</hi> by <hi>private Prayer, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination</hi> of Conſcience, and <hi>compoſing our minds</hi> to a <hi>ſerious temper</hi> and awful apprehenſions of God, whom we are to worſhip, <hi>before we go to Church; Recollections</hi> in convenient time when we are <hi>return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Examining</hi> and <hi>Inſtructing our Children</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> cauſing them to <hi>attend Reading</hi> and <hi>Family-prayers</hi> and <hi>Pſalms</hi> for ſome reaſonable time, and <hi>reſtraining them</hi> all the day long from <hi>many Liberties</hi> uſual on common dayes, all theſe can have, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves no ſin in them; but are pious and commendable, and will turn to our own and our Families account one day, if not at preſent.</p>
            <p>Herein, let the <hi>forced Conceſſions</hi> of ſome of the <hi>keeneſt diſputants</hi> in behalf of <hi>Sunday Sports</hi> be heard.
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:152772:7"/>
               <q>1. Whatever may hinder either the worſhip of God it ſelf, or our profiting therein; ſhould be forborn and avoided.—For all ſuch things, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <note place="inline">
                     <hi>Ironſides</hi> 7 <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. Cap.</hi> 24. <hi>p.</hi> 224. <hi>p.</hi> 269.</note> as keep us from, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us in the Publik Worſhip, are altogether unlawful on the Lords Day. (2.) It is not unlawful to obſerve the Lords Day with as great ſtrictneſs as the Jews did the Sabbath: provided we have no opinion, that ſuch reſt is of neceſſity to be obſerved, under pain of ſin, putting Religion therein <hi>[p.</hi> 227.] And that we cenſure not others who uſe their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; nor out of a ſuperſtitious fear decline the doing any work of Neceſſity or Charity, the benefit whereof would be utterly loſt; were the preſent opportunity neglected (3.) Thoſe who can and will ſpend the vacant time of the Lords Day, in the private Exerciſes of piety, ought not to be diſcountenanced or diſheartened, but encouraged rather <hi>p.</hi> 268.</q> In a word, let all follow thus what their own conſciences, when they are ſerious cannot (what the very learned defenders of ſuch Liberties as they are fond of, when they conſulted their own conſciences, could not) but confeſs, and there is little queſtion but the whole Lords Day will be generally ſpent as in this diſcourſe is preſſed.</p>
            <p>It may be obſerved, I have not preſſed ſuch ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as exclude <hi>due refreſhments,</hi> and keeping the ſpirits in vigour and cheerfulneſs: Nor do I ſuppoſe
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:152772:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe expreſſions <hi>giving the whole day to God,</hi> and the like, which I have produced out of holy mens writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, uſe to be taken in ſuch a <hi>rigorous ſenſe</hi> that the private and publick duties having been conſcientiouſly performed and ſecured, any ſhould conclude it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for people to walk abroad awhile in freſh air, and Contemplate the works of God, and enjoy themſelves in beholding and moderately uſing them. No nor for them ſitting at home, to let drop, at their Meals or otherwiſe, out of the times of their Devotions, ſomething of innocent cheerful diſcourſe; or, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion offers, to ſpeak touching matters of concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them, or of the common Occurrents in Human affairs: though the leſs of this the better. In a word: That, which I inſiſt on as required, is, that <hi>All this day, Chriſtians take care, not to diſorder their hearts for the worſhip of God,</hi> but that, after their ſeveral refreſhments, they may return again, with compoſed minds, to the thoughts of God and Heaven, and their duties; and in the Evening ſweetly commit their Souls and Bodys, their family and ſubſtance, to the Divine protection, repoſing themſelves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably in Gods favour, and in the good hopes of his acceptance in Chriſt Jeſus. If thus the day be ſpent, it is as much given to God, as our preſent condition will ſuffer us.</p>
            <p>But will ſome ſay, if this be all you contend for, who denies the Divine obligation of the Lords Day, or its obſervation, thus ſtated? I anſwer, many have done and ſtill do deny it. Onely it comes to paſs in this particular caſe (what does more generally,
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:152772:8"/> when men write in defence of ſuch Doctrines, which their <hi>Intereſt</hi> rather than their <hi>Conſcience</hi> approves) that by their own conceſſions in conſcience, they ſometimes contradict, what they have ſaid for Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. And hence it is that we may eaſily pick, out of our very Adverſaries writings, ſundry memorable paſſages which favour us, and ſo ſometimes they deny, what we contend for, and ſometimes they grant it. In the mean time, what is the effect which theſe Learned mens denying (flatly and directly) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in their writings; ſometimes in ordinary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (and it were to be wiſhed they did it not in their moſt ſacred diſcourſes too) <hi>what</hi> I ſay <hi>is the effect</hi> which their <hi>denying the morality of the fourth command</hi> has in the World? Truely nothing but the <hi>growth of Licentiouſneſs and Irreligion.</hi> I know they <hi>pretend</hi> onely to <hi>Innocent Liberty,</hi> and eaſing peoples Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of endleſs Scruples: But is not Conſcience eaſy enough by aſſerting ſuch a Morality and Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Chriſtian Sabbath as above? They would be underſtood to deny meerly ſuch a <hi>Natural Morality</hi> of the <hi>letter of the fourth Command,</hi> as there is in the firſt, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me.</hi> That is <hi>thou ſhall worſhip the Lord thy God and him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhalt thou ſerve;</hi> The Juſtneſs and Obligation whereof, the very light of Nature, or reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very Terms, doth dictate to us. They would be content, they'l ſay, to <hi>allow</hi> unto the <hi>fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> a kind of <hi>Equitahle morality</hi> and own the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand too in ſome regard as <hi>poſitively Moral.</hi> Nor do I deny, but that when they thus ſpeak, they ſpeak
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:152772:8"/> what, if ſtrictly taken and well underſtood, is reaſon; and as farr forth as there is reaſon and truth in it, I have owned it: But the <hi>People</hi> in the mean time <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi> not the <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>diſtinct degrees of Morality.</hi> And when they read or here learned men deny the Morality of the fourth Commandment, they <hi>take all at Random;</hi> and think themſelves at liberty. They ſay with themſelves <q>If indeed we keep the Lords Day, tis true we do well; but if we ſee fit to travel, or if we take our pleaſure, or bodily eaſe, all that day, we ſin not: For the fourth command is not moral: And the Lords Day is onely a Church Holy day. All dayes under the Goſpel are equal as our moſt learned Doctors teach us.</q> Now is it not evident that by theſe Terms, ſuch learned men have betrayed poor plain people into Licentiouſneſs Prophaneſs and Irreligion? And were it not better, to be more cautious, and allow all the Decalogue to be moral, as indeed it is in one degree or other (though one command, or one duty, may ſometimes give place to another, as <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to <hi>Mercy)</hi> and onely to teach, that the fourth command had <hi>one ſenſe to the Jews,</hi> and <hi>another to us</hi> Chriſtians; as had the Preface to all the commands, <hi>Thy God that brought thee out of the Land,</hi> &amp;c, and divers paſſages in other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. And finally to preſs the <hi>Evangelical ſenſe</hi> of all, which none queſtion to be moral enough: were not this I ſay much better, than by our Learning and exactneſs, by terms unknown to Scripture, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions not underſtood by common people, to become Authors of their ſins? I leave this to the conſcience
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:152772:9"/> and conſideration of all prudent and ſerious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and paſs on to another point in the following diſcourſe, which ſome haply may cenſure.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the <hi>conſtant publick Duties of the Lords day,</hi> I have reckoned <hi>Communicating.</hi> And herein ſome will conceive I have gone beyond the Law of our Church, which Requires, as they may think, by her Rubrick, that the people Communicate but <hi>three times a year.</hi> To this I ſay, this is indeed the leaſt which, according to the Laws of our Church, will exempt people from Cenſure; but this is far from being all, which ſhe would bring her Sons to. For ſhe has provided a Communion-ſervice, not only for every Lords day, but for every holyday in the year; And by diverſe paſſages of the Rubrick (more than I am willing to inſiſt on at preſent) it appears ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires more. I may not wave that particular Text of the Rubrick <hi>In Cathedral and Collegiate Churches, where there are many Prieſts, every Sunday at the leaſt, except they have a reaſonable cauſe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp;c.</hi> And further to back this Rubrick, I muſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly profeſs, I do not ſee how any Chriſtian can ſatisfie himſelf, that he walks according to Scripture and Primitive Rule, who (except in caſes of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or want of opportunity) Communicates ſeldomer than each Lords day. In the beginning of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, 'tis plain from <hi>Acts</hi> ii. 42. they Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated dayly: And this Cuſtome continued in a great part of the Church for above four hundred Years after Chriſt, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> particularly (who dyed not till the year of our Lord. 430) not only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:152772:9"/> it as then Cuſtomary, but exhorts to it. I will not urge, that in the Romiſh Church we may obſerve the Footſteps of this practice ſtill, from their dayly private Maſſes. But I muſt note that the <hi>(minimum quod ſic</hi> or) moſt ſeldom returns, that we read the Adminiſtration hereof had, in the Apoſtolical age, were on every Lords Day. <hi>On the firſt day of the week, when the Diſciples came together to break</hi> Bread &amp;c. Acts xxi. And I wiſh thoſe words which St. <hi>Paul</hi> reports as in the Body of the Inſtitution, from our Saviour, and which our Church from St. <hi>Paul</hi> inſerts into the form of Conſecration, <hi>Do this as oft as ye Drink it in remembrance of me,</hi> had been better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered (eſpecially as they ſtand in the Original) than they are, by moſt interpreters. I think I could eaſily and evidently make out, that they import no leſs than an expreſs command to this purpoſe, <hi>every day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you publickly aſſemble, ſee you celebrate my Supper.</hi> Let this be a conſtant part of every days publick Worſhip. But the due Deduction of this ſenſe would take up more room, than I may at preſent allow my ſelf. However ſtill I challenge, any inſtance to be produced from Scripture, of Chriſtians in the Apoſtles age communicating ſeldomer than each Sunday. I may therefore reaſonably conclude touching this Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of our Church, not puniſhing the negligence of ſuch as Communicate but thrice a year, as our Lord does touching Divorce, <hi>Becauſe of the hardneſs of mens hearts it is ſuffered to them; but from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was not ſo;</hi> nor is it the mind of our Church it ſhould be ſo. The Lords Supper was and ſtill
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:152772:10"/> ought to be, as occaſion requires, Adminiſtred ofte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than on each Lords day; but, it being plain that the conſtant celebration of the Lords Supper and the Lords Day coming in as it were together, and that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any order or practice of the Apoſtles, nor any Canon of the Church, has ſeparated them, or exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Lords Supper, from the publick duties of the Lords Day; the ſeparation of them, which is now come into the Church, can onely be made by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and degeneracy of the latter Chriſtian ages: And whether either the corruption or degeneracy of others, will be a good plea for the like in us one day, it behoves us to conſider in time. For my own part I am reſolved, I and as many as I can prevail with ſhall never run the venture. I will Communicate or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter, if I can get but three Chriſtians with me, at leaſt every Lords day: And let others forbear it at their peril, and as they will anſwer, before God and Chriſt the Righteous Judge, at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>It remains now I onely add a word or two for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving thoſe neglects which in the begining I taxed, as ſo frequent, eſpecially amongſt the Iriſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, in moſt Country Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Neglect of afternoon publick worſhip,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Catechiſing</hi> youth with that conſtancy that the Laws have enjoyned, is ordinarily pleaded to be <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated,</hi> or made in a manner unavoidable, by the <hi>diſtance of the Pariſhioners</hi> dwellings from the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Country. But to this I anſwer (1.) This is not ſo conſtant every where, but that there are ſome competent number of Proteſtant Inhabitants within
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:152772:10"/> ſuch convenient diſtance, as that there might be a <hi>ſmaller Congregation in the afternoon:</hi> And then, families might be warned by turns, and in courſe, to ſend their younger people on afternoons to Catechiſm; which thing might be made convenient by a hundred little Contrivances, that the meaneſt capacities (if people had but a good heart for their duty) would quickly find out. As for inſtance, if my young people came with me to Church in the morning, I could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let them ſtay a dinner-time at their Neighbours houſe neerer the Church than my own, that they may be at Evening ſervice and Catechiſm. If they do not, I can order them to be ready, by ſuch a time as I come home, to take the Horſe or Horſes, with which I and others of my Family went to Church in the Morning, and they will be early enough for their duty. A true good will, and a litle zeal for our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, may find out more and better expedients as cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances may varie. (2) If the <hi>Miniſters houſe</hi> be ſo far diſtant from the Church, are his and all ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Religious <hi>Neighbours Houſes,</hi> ſo out of the way, that there can be no ſmall afternoon-Aſſemblies, in any of them? If any be unwilling to have their houſe ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly troubled every Lords Day, convenient <hi>Houſes in ſeveral diſtricts</hi> may be taken by turns, and in the morning notice given at the Church, that evening Prayers will be at ſuch a Family this day, and at ſuch a one the next Lords Day <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now here young people may conveniently appear for Catechiſm. This will be made much the more tolerable to poorer Inhabitants, if there be a rule ſet up, that there be no
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:152772:11"/> ſuch cuſtom at any time permitted as giving Drink and Entertainments to the Neighbours that Aſſemble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any more than there is at Church. But I am aſhamed to deſcend to ſuch minute matters; I leave this to good Chriſtians piety and prudence: And take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in a word of the other more groſs neglect above taxed, namely the <hi>Clergies coming to their Cures but once a fortnight,</hi> or ſeldomer.</p>
            <p>Where the ſlenderneſs of the maintenance is ſuch, that better proviſion cannot be made, this is to be born and lamented. But in other caſes I hope the Governours of the Church will not bear with it, and I am ſure, it is inexcuſable on any other ſcore, ſave that of neceſſity. At leaſt it is no excuſe to an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent (what is too uſualy pleaded) <hi>My Neighbours are content with once a fortnight,</hi> what need I trouble my ſelf any more? To this I ſay (1) This plea is made many times where it is not true: Some Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are content ſo, not all. And they, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo confident, as to complain to their Miniſters face, will do it in his abſence: Or, though haply they dare not accuſe him to his Biſhop, will mutter of it to perſons of meaner rank, and amongſt themſelves at home. (2) If the people are ſo ſatisfied, yet is not this practice a ſatisfaction to the Law of God, or to the Church; nor will it be a ſatisfaction one day to a mans conſcience. In ſhort, Is the Lords Day to be kept holy? Is the publick worſhip thereon a Chriſtian Duty or No? If it be, How then dare any perſon, to whom the Charge of Souls is committed, be Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to them of Neglecting one, or Prophaning the
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:152772:11"/> other? Will not one Day all ſuch his Peoples neglects and Prophanations, all their Alehouſe-meetings, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, Drunkeneſs and other Debaucheries, acted on the Lords Day, be charged on ſuch their Miniſter? And laſtly, in caſe the people really be thus content, it is a ſhrewd Argument they are groſly Lukewarm and Irreligious. Now it would be enquired, and will one day, is not the peoples lukewarmneſs, their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſin? Has not he been a Precedent to them therein? Has not his neglect of his duty bred them thereto? If they had been better inſtructed, more conſtantly warned &amp; called upon, they would have had more knowledg, more warmth, more ſence of their duty, more Faith and belief of its obligation, than to have ſatisfied themſelves with ſuch ſlender atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God, and ſo little minding their Souls. But 'tis time to finiſh this large Porch to ſo ſmall a Fabrick.</p>
            <p>What I have ſaid, is from a ſerious conſcience of my own Duty, and in the real fear of God. If it have effect to amend any, I ſhall rejoyce therein and bleſs God. If it have not, I have born my teſtimony in this great and publick concern of Religion. I will not by Gods grace be an offender againſt my own rules: And I truſt one day, that whatever my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Omiſſions have been in other caſes, (as they are and have been, God help me, very many) yet that God through Chriſt will one day pardon them all, and judge touching me, as to this Matter that <hi>Liberavi animam meam.</hi> God deliver us all from thoſe judgments, both here and hereafter, which our Relapſes after our late Repentance, and
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:152772:12"/> vows in our Miſeries, or to ſpeak it in Scripture lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which our <hi>returning to our vomit,</hi> may moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring upon us, and for which I muſt declare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the World, I dayly expect yet a <hi>return of an over flowing ſcourge,</hi> in one kind or other, if not prevented by a ſudden Reformation; to which I know no one thing that will be of more general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement, than a ſtrict and conſtant obſervation of the Lords Day, the thing I have aymed at in this paper, and in the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cork.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov:</hi> 17. 1696</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>THE Reader may be pleaſed to underſtand the whole Paragraph included in Crochets thus [ ] <hi>pag.</hi> 13 and 14. as alſo another out of <hi>Ignatius, pag.</hi> 27, 28. were paſſed over, for haſte's ſake, at the delivery of this Sermon, but were notwithſtanding now thought fit to appear in their places.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 19. l. 21. for <hi>thereon</hi> read <hi>then.</hi> p. 26. l. 7. for <hi>ſeen</hi> r. <hi>been.</hi> p. 28. l. 26, 27. the words <hi>(namely by our Lords appointment, as in other caſes)</hi> ſhould not have been put in Italick letter, for they are not the Fathers words. p. 36. in the margin r. <hi>from ill imputations.</hi> In Pref. p. iii. l. <hi>penult.</hi> r. <hi>a Virtual.</hi> p. ix. l. 3. r. ſeverely. Other literal eſcapes crave pardon on courſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152772:12"/>
            <head>A SERMON Touching The LORDS DAY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Revelation I. Ver. x. Firſt part.</bibl>
               <q>I was in the Spirit on the Lords Day.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FRom theſe words I purpoſe to <note place="margin">The deſign of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> aſſert, Firſt, the Divine Right of the Lords Day; Then, the true Chriſtian way of keeping it. <hi>I was in the Spirit on the Lords Day;</hi> which day I ſhall not doubt, after ſome of the Fathers, but eſpecially after our own Church, both in her Cannons and much oftner, and more
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152772:13"/> expreſly in the Homily <hi>concerning the Time and Place of Prayer,</hi> to ſtile a Chriſtian <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>I</label> And firſt as to its Divine Right; 'Tis the Lords Day. In the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <note place="margin">The ſtyle of the Text aſſerts the Lords Day to be of Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</note> Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. An Epithet [or Term] but once more occuring in Holy Writt, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 20. where the Holy Communion is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Lords Supper:</hi> Both equally the Lords, becauſe both, by the ſame appropriative term, ſtyled ſuch: And if both e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually his, then both Inſtituted by him.</p>
            <p>Touching the Lords Inſtitution of his Supper none doubteth: And why ſhould any doubt of his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Day? when 'tis the ſame Lord to whom both are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And when by a word peculiar, or which ſeems coined on purpoſe to aſſert his claim, he, the ſame Lord, has avouched them both his; and nothing elſe, throughout the whole Scripture, in the ſame ſtile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouched his.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152772:13"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>II</label> Yet are there amongſt us, I mean that call themſelves <hi>Sons of our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of the term,</hi> a Chriſtian Sabbata</note> 
               <hi>Church, too many,</hi> who really <hi>place the Lords Day upon the ſame level with</hi> (if not below) <hi>other Church Holy-days:</hi> they do ſo at leaſt, if we may <hi>judg</hi> of their <hi>Faith by their Works,</hi> which ſome think ſurer both diſcoveries and teſts of what men believe, than any words can be. I crave your patience therefore while I remove that inſolent demand, (it is ſo at leaſt, as ſome uſe to put it) How can you make out the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Day? and where find you, or what ground is there for, a Septenary Chriſtian Sabbath?</p>
            <p>The anſwer is: A <hi>Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> according as <hi>Chriſtian Temples,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian Prieſthood</hi> and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>appendages</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> we cannot expect to meet with elder than Chriſtianity it ſelf. But <hi>a Sabbath,</hi> no leſs than <hi>Temples</hi> or places dedicated to Divine Worſhip, no leſs than a <hi>Prieſthood</hi> and ſuch like adjuncts of Worſhip we find much elder, even before <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152772:14"/> as well as under it; and all <hi>perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> all <hi>poſitively moral;</hi> though as the new Law came, it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt all, and particularly the Sabbath, received thereby ſome new modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations as well as new names. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>III</label> Now the ſum of what I ſhall advance to <note place="margin">The ſum of the further proof.</note> clear this matter, ſhall be directed to thoſe three Points.</p>
            <p>A Sabbath or certain day of reſt for Publick Worſhip is dictated by the Law natural.</p>
            <p>A Seventh day by God's eldeſt Laws poſitive.</p>
            <p>This Seventh day by the Law Chriſtian; I mean the eldeſt Records of our Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I muſt for that brevity's ſake, which uſe has made neceſſary, wave the deductions I had prepared at length from the Law of Nature, as to this matter, and ſay in few words, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>IV</label> 
               <hi>Nature</hi> teaches, <hi>God is publickly to be worſhipped. Publick Worſhip</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Natural reaſon for a Sabbath.</note> be without <hi>times publickly aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> for it. If ſuch times be either too <hi>ſhort,</hi> or too <hi>ſeldom</hi> returning,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152772:14"/> the impreſſions of God, of Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of an Unſeen World, which ſuch Publick Worſhip is deſigned to make on the Worſhippers, will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be very ſlight, or by infrequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy defaced beyond recovery: In ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which caſes, <hi>the worſhip</hi> is rendred <hi>unprofitable.</hi> Further, ſince 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> for us intirely to attend <hi>two things at once,</hi> therefore <hi>on ſuch days</hi> as this Publick Worſhip is to be paid, <hi>common buſineſs is to be laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</hi> There muſt then, through all Bodies or Societies of People, be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent vacations from ordinary Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, for the Publick Worſhip of God: That is a Sabbath or fixt and certain time of <hi>holy reſt; for the publick Offices of Religion is from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>V</label> For ſuch reaſons as theſe (to come briefly to <hi>Law poſitive)</hi> we may <note place="margin">The firſt inſtitution of a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath in Paradiſe.</note> with humble reverence conceive, it was, that the moſt holy and wiſe God has provided there ſhould be extant a very early Revelation, and <hi>moſt ancient Record of his reſting</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon the <hi>finiſhing of the</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152772:15"/> 
               <hi>Creation, Gen.</hi> ii. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>Thus the Heavens and the Earth were finiſhed, and all the hoſt of them; and on the Seventh day God ended his work which he had made, and reſted the Seventh day from all his works which he had made, and God bleſſed the Seventh day and ſanctified it: becauſe in it he had reſted from all his work which God created and made.</hi> By theſe words there muſt be deſigned either a direct <hi>Command given,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>a precedent,</hi> in the Oeconomy of God's actions, <hi>propoſed,</hi> which might be <hi>inſtead of a Command</hi> for keeping a Seventh day from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining Holy unto God. For mine own part I am of the mind, with the <note n="*" place="margin">Rivet <hi>alledges</hi> 30 <hi>of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea: Beſides di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe of the Fathers and even of the Romaniſts.</hi> Diſſert de Orig. Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat cap. 1</note> generality of Interpreters, both antient and modern, It is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. For what leſs can be meant by Gods <hi>bleſſing the Seventh day and ſanctifying it. Let bleſſing it</hi> ſignifie what it can, <hi>ſanctifying it</hi> in the very primary ſenſe of the word ſignifies, ſeparating it, namely to Religious purpoſes. Now how could it be thus ſeparated without a Command?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152772:15"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>VI</label> The conceit of a <hi>Prolepſis</hi> here, or that this was ſpoken and recorded <note place="margin">Objections anſwered.</note> out of time, only as a kind of ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating the Fourth Commandment, beſides that it is forced, if not raſh (and with all likelihood, in that great perſon who firſt advanced the Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, due meerely to an exceſs of zeal againſt Judaiſm) is, no better than a bold begging of the Queſtion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ground in the Text or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text: rather indeed, againſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt import and ſcope of both. For 'tis plain thence, that the Six days and the works thereof being ended, God did then [or on that firſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day of time] actualy <hi>reſt,</hi> that is as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> expounds it, <hi>ceaſe from making other kinds of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> But how incongruous is it to refer things ſpoken continuedly, and connected as done in one and the ſame inſtant, to refer ſuch things, I ſay, to ſo diſtant parts of time? <hi>(viz.)</hi> Gods <hi>reſting</hi> to the firſt Seventh day of time, and his <hi>bleſſing and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Seventh day</hi> to another like Seventh day, above two thouſand-years
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152772:16"/> after? This is forcing wide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder what God joined. Who can digeſt this Paraphraſe on the Text? <q>God having finiſht his Six days work, then Reſted the Seventh day; and two thouſand five hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and fourteen years after, he Sanctified the like day of the Week, or appointed it to be kept Holy.</q> If ſo, I ſay here are <hi>two Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth days</hi> ſpoken <hi>of in one and the ſame word:</hi> the Seventh day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God reſted, and the Seventh day which recurred in the weekly courſe ſo long after; which I think all men of ſenſe muſt acknowledge to be as great a violence as was ever uſed to a word; and never allowed in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting any other place of Scripture; wherefore not to be admitted here.</p>
            <p>Add hereto, that when this Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution came to be reinforced at <hi>Sinai</hi> (the obſervation of the Sabbath hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been diſcontinued by the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> during their travel, and perhaps during their bondage too) the very wording of the Command beſpeaks the thing commanded to have been
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152772:16"/> of elder uſe. For <hi>Remembring,</hi> is of things <hi>formerly known.</hi> Now <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Sabbath day to keep it holy,</hi> is the very letter of the Text: On which the Jews tell us, as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> hinſelf reports it, that God ſanctifyed the Seventh day from the beginning, by reſting thereon from all his works; and therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid <hi>Remember the Sabbath day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be objected the ſanctifying a Seventh day could be no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from the beginning, for then we ſhould have had it amongſt the <hi>Precepts of the Sons of Noah,</hi> I anſwer (to ſay nothing of the uncertainty of the Tradition of thoſe Precepts any otherwiſe than as they are grounded in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s writings) Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have we in theſe Precepts any mention of Sacrifices, of Prayer, of a Prieſthood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet are we ſure that <hi>Adam</hi> had Command, or which is much the ſame, Directions or Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations from God touching all theſe; And that they were practiſed by him and his poſterity before the Law. If it be ſaid theſe were includ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152772:17"/> in the Precept [Gnal Birkath Haſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhem] <hi>touching Divine Worſhip,</hi> (or, <hi>againſt profaning the Name of God.</hi> for I think the words may be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred either way) I ſay, ſo may this of the Sabbath well be too: and the rather, in as much as it being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perform an outward act, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out time, the ſame Law, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that Act, muſt be underſtood to command time for the doing it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>VII</label> But ſuppoſing (not granting) no proper command then given, yet <note place="margin">Gods Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</note> can it not be denyed, that God by declaring, and cauſing to be record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this his Procedure, of gradually finiſhing all his works in Six days, and reſting the Seventh did propoſe his practice as <hi>a precedent</hi> to our firſt Parents, for their Ordinary paſſing their time. God was under no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to take up Six days in making the World. He could have done it, had he pleaſed in Six hours; Nay in Six minutes. Nor was he under any fatigue by working, ſo that he needed to talk of reſting; therefore his proceeding thus, and not wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152772:17"/> up his procedure in darkneſs and ſilence, but making all matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, and a ſtanding Record, plainly ſhews he deſign'd thereby to teach <hi>Adam</hi> and in him all mankind, they were neither to live Idle any of their days (for God worked Six) nor to work each day as they liſted, for God reſted the Seventh and bleſſed it, that is he made it a Holy Reſt, a Sabbath.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>VIII</label> From this either Command or Precedent without all doubt proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <note place="margin">The Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law.</note> even before <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, <hi>the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of The Sabbath</hi> amongſt all ſuch at leaſt as adhered to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God: which obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation has been by diverſe learned men amply proved both from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Fathers: the proof is too long, here to inſert. I will only mention that <hi>St. Epiphanius</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinguiſhes betwixt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>The Sabbath by nature</hi> [or Law Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall] <hi>appointed from the beginning,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>The Sabbath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained under the Law;</hi> which ſhews a Sabbath before the Law was in his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152772:18"/> time, or at leaſt by him, in no wiſe doubted of.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>IX</label> 
               <hi>For mine own part,</hi> I am in that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox (with ſubmiſſion to better <note place="margin">Tis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Adam and Eve obſerved the Sabbath in Paradiſe.</note> judgments) that the Sabbath was kept by <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what the <hi>Rabbies</hi> talk to the contrary) and that it was the only intire day he ſtood in his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency. For that <hi>Adam fell not on the Sixth day</hi> (as many have thought) <hi>Eves</hi> being Created late that Day, and God's pronouncing <hi>all very good</hi> for the <hi>concluſion of the day</hi> ſeem to me little leſs than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration. And whereas God having finiſhed his works, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly reſted, bleſſed the Seventh day, and ſanctified it, it <hi>looks not likely</hi> that the <hi>day</hi> which God <hi>bleſſed and ſanctifyed</hi> ſhould be the day on which the <hi>curſe enter'd into the World.</hi> Therefore I ſay it ſeems to me moſt probable, that our firſt Parents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the revelation of Gods reſting, upon the very day he reſted, and ſo kept the firſt Seventh or Sabbath day in Paradiſe.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152772:18"/>
            <p> But be that as it ſhall, I contend not. [However, I think it cannot be denyed, but to them, who in thoſe <hi>early</hi> ages knew the Hiſtory of the Creation (which undoubtedly <hi>Seth</hi>'s Race in general till the Floud, and many of them long after it, did know) there was, as alſo there will be to the end of the World, more reaſon for keeping one Day in Seven, than one Day in Six, or one in Eight, Nine, or Ten, <hi/> for that the firſt Period, by which, even from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, Time was diſtinguiſht, was that of a ſeptenary of Days or a Week: <hi>God worked Six Days, and reſted the Seventh.</hi> Nor is it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, but that to ſuch a perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical diſtinction of days may that paſſage <hi>(Gen.</hi> iv. 3.) be referr'd. <hi>At the end of days,</hi> (ſo ſtands it in the Hebrew Text, what we too largely render, <hi>In proceſs of time)</hi> that is, not improbably I ſay, upon the Revolution of ſome certain Week, namely upon ſome Sabbath Day, <hi>Cain and Abel brought their Offerings.</hi> The like may be believed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152772:19"/> of thoſe Texts in <hi>Job,</hi> (a Hiſtory generally granted to be elder than the Law) <hi>There was a day when the Sons of God</hi> (as the Holy Race are ſtiled, <hi>Gen.</hi> vi. 2.) <hi>came to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues before the Lord, Job</hi> i. 6. and ii. 1. This cannot be better fix'd, than as by Learned Perſons it is, on the Sabbath Day,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>X</label> But to paſs the Patriarchal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation] There can be no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <note place="margin">The fourth Command, of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue, Morall.</note> of the command of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath from <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> amongſt the other Commands of the Decalogue. It is delivered in a ſtyle more em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical than any of the other: And therefore a man would wonder, that it alone of all the Ten ſhould not be Moral. <hi>Remember the Sabbath Day to keep it holy:</hi> which words, that they ſhould injoyn matter of meer Ceremony, of concernment only to the Jews, and of no laſting obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Chriſtians, as to a weekly day of a holy reſt for the publick Service of God, the Arguments which I have yet known offered, I muſt confeſs are much too feeble to perſwade.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152772:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>'Tis true indeed the Apoſtle tells us <hi>(Colloſſ.</hi> ii. 16, 17.) the Jewiſh differencings of <hi>Meats and Drinks,</hi> their <hi>Holy days, their New Moons and Sabbaths</hi> [Sabbath days, is not in the original, but Sabbaths] that is their great variety of Carnal Reſts, their Sabbaths of Years, and their, Sabbaths of Months, and their Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths of Days, for all theſe they had; their Feaſt-Sabbaths and Faſt-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and the peculiar ways of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them, by feeding on certain appointed Meats, and abſtaining from others uſual enough at common ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; all theſe <hi>were a ſhadow of things to come.</hi> But will this which concerns only a part of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Law, evacuate one of the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Decalogue, all whoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Commands are confeſſedly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral? Let that preciſe Seventh day, namely the laſt day of the Week be Temporary, and only obligatory till the fullneſs of time were come, Let <hi>bodily reſt, and ſtrictneſs of the reſt</hi> thereon injoyned to the Jews, not to do ſo much of <hi>ſervile work</hi> as to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152772:20"/> 
               <hi>kindle a fire</hi> thereon: let theſe I ſay <hi>be Ceremonial, ſignificative of a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Reſt under the Goſpel;</hi> Was therefore a <hi>weekly Sabbath</hi> holy to God <hi>for his publick worſhip a ſhadow too?</hi> and no certain conſtant propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time to be allowed as ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to God, becauſe the multitude of Jewiſh Feſtivals, and even the Judaiſm and Ceremonialneſs of the Sabbath, were to be abrogated, which is the utmoſt can be conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hence. Let us beware of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus, there being no reaſon for ſuch concluſion as the Objectours would infer.</p>
            <p>Before we reſolve of laying aſide any part of the Law of God, let us conſider it better.</p>
            <p>There was <hi>more in the Command</hi> then a <hi>meer Carnall Reſt,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more than a Ceremony, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to keep holy the Sabbath day.</hi> Reſting from common labours there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a Ceremony; but ſomewhat of this Reſt a Ceremony neceſſary and pre-requiſite to the keeping of it Holy; the <hi>main ſubſtance</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152772:20"/> or chief matter commanded, was <hi>keeping it holy;</hi> that is, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God thereon, in publick; contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating him and his works, in ſecret; being wholy free to him, for that day. Is Divine Worſhip and Holy Contemplation, and Converſe with God a Ceremony?</p>
            <p>Further; Somewhat there is too in the Command, as to other days, which we cannot account Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious. Is it a Ceremony, a thing in it ſelf meerly Indifferent, how we ſpend our time? the Regulation of which is moſt plainly the ſumme of this Commandment. <hi>Six days</hi> to be ſpent <hi>in our common calling,</hi> as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſuch or ſuch condition, or occupation: And a <hi>Seventh in our holy calling</hi> as worſhippers of the true God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>XI</label> Let who will ſay <hi>this Command is meerly Ceremonial,</hi> I am ſure <hi>no</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Church herein.</note> 
               <hi>Son of the Church of England muſt ſay ſo.</hi> For if this as well as the other nine Commandments be not, in the Judgment of our Church, a part of the Moral Law, why were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152772:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> we juſt now upon our knees, before God, by order of our Church, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods mercy for our breaking it, and his Grace for inclining our hearts to keep it? What to keep a Jewiſh abrogate Ceremony?</p>
            <p>No no, Its moral obligation is by our Church and us, before God, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly acknowledged in theſe very Prayers, as oft as we make them: and further, as before hinted <hi>in the Homily of the time and place of Prayer,</hi> to which I refer my ſelf, it is more at large aſſerted. Now ſure our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mother never intended both her ſelf to falſify with God and Man, and to breed her Children too, to ſo hopeful a practice: A hopeful practice, I ſay, to falſify with God in her Prayers, even in her moſt ſolemn Office, the Communion Service; and with Man, in her form of Doctrine or Homilies; both which ſhe does, if this be not her ſence. It is then the Judgment of our Church what we have otherwiſe proved, that by the eldeſt poſitive Law of God, a Seventh day is holy to him.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152772:21"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>XII</label> And <hi>this Seventh day</hi> is <hi>now the Lords day,</hi> or <hi>Firſt day of the Week,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Peoples obſerving the Lords day inſtead of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</note> by the <hi>Law Chriſtian;</hi> Here alſo the evidence is too long to give it in, in full, at preſent. But.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a word or two for the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of</hi> the Firſt day of the Week under the Chriſtian ſtate. The very ſelf ſame reaſons, with which God of old bound the Seventh day-Sabbath on <hi>Adam,</hi> and on the Jews, bind the obſervation of the Firſt day of the Week upon us Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The reaſon to <hi>Adam</hi> was, <hi>on the Sixth day God ended his works, that he had Created, and Reſted the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth:</hi> In like manner, the Seventh day of the Week being ended our Lord Jeſus had finiſht his work of the new Creation, in that thereon <hi>by his reſurrection,</hi> he made Man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the ſecond time happily immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; and having wreſted from Death its Sting, from the Grave its Victory, opened the Kingdom of Heaven to all Believers; entred into it himſelf, and <hi>began the everlaſting Sabbatiſm</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152772:22"/> 
               <hi>of the new World:</hi> Which work had he not finiſht, what had it advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged poor mankind to have been Created once? Alas! had not the work of Redemption been compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Mans firſt Creation had only ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitated him to have been eternally miſerable. This reaſon therefore from the Divine Reſt thereon, holds, to us Chriſtians, much ſtronger for this Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon to the Jews in ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all was, becauſe <hi>the Lord thy God brought thee out of the Land of Egypt through a mighty hand and an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arm, therefore the Lord thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut:</hi> v. 15.</note> 
               <hi>God commanded thee to keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day.</hi> On the Sabbath or Seventh day, ſay the Jewiſh Doctors, their Forefathers ſung their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Triumphal Hymne</hi> to God at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> over the drowned Egyptians. And <hi>on the firſt day of the Week, while it was yet early,</hi> Our Lord roſe from the dead, as out of a Red Sea of Bloud, and brought with him the raiſed Bodies of many Saints which ſlept (the Bodies of our firſt Parents
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152772:22"/> ſaith an old tradition) and having thus reſcued mankind from under the bonds of Sin and Death, and of him that had the power of Death, the Devil, he made a ſhew of them <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing over them openly.</hi> Thus alſo there is the like reaſon for the Firſt day of the Week to be a Chriſtian Sabbath, as there was for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day to be the Jewiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>XIII</label> But where have we any <hi>Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for this day,</hi> in the Records of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Lords Day.</hi> 1. <hi>By Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </note> New Teſtament?</p>
            <p>I anſwer <hi>our Lord Inſtituted it</hi> the moſt effectual way imaginable, namely <hi>by his own practice.</hi> His fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, if not conſtant, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his Diſciples on this day, <hi>dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Forty days</hi> after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, his meeting them in their Aſſemblies, ſometimes with ſome of them <hi>breaking bread,</hi> with all of them always <hi>ſpeaking of the things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Kingdom of God,</hi> was as ſolemn a dedication of this day to the Chriſtian worſhip, as well can be conceived. <hi>John,</hi> XX. 19. <hi>The ſame day</hi> (which was ver. 1. <hi>the firſt</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152772:23"/> 
               <hi>day of the week) at evening the doors being ſhut for fear of the Jews, came Jeſus where the Diſciples were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and ſtood in the midſt of them and ſaid, Peace be unto you;</hi> and ſhewed them his hands and his feet. <hi>And on the Eighth day,</hi> which (reckoning after the Jewiſh uſe, incluſively) was the next Lords day, they are met again <hi>(ver</hi> 26.) and now <hi>Thomas</hi> was with them: for the courſe of Sunday-Aſſemblies was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun) <hi>and Jeſus came again the Doors being ſhut, and ſaid Peace be unto you.</hi> Then addreſſing himſelf more particularly to <hi>Thomas,</hi> for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his doubts, and thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the Faith of them all, he pronounces a Bleſſing, not only on them, but on all that ſhould believe on him to the end of the World. How often, in thoſe Forty days, our Lord appeared to his Diſciples, it has not pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely to ſet down. <hi>Two Lords days apparitions</hi> to them, in their aſſembly, we have thus ſeen expreſly on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: and on the ſame days, ſeveral
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152772:23"/> private apparitions to diverſe of them apart, are recorded alſo, which we may not ſtand to examine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the moſt famous and often fore-appointed appearance, on the mountain <hi>in Galilee</hi> (a place diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant enough from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that none might fear diſturbance from the Chief Prieſts and their Partiſans) is by ſome very great men placed <hi>on the Lords day:</hi> at which time he was ſeen of above Five hundred Brethren at once, ſpeaking no doubt (as his uſe was) of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God. And being that this his appearance cannot, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtently with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s account, be <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xv. 6, 7.</note> coincident with that at his Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is little probability (all circumſtances being conſidered) for placing it on any other day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſt of all,</hi> our Lord choſe to bleſs the Firſt day of the Week by that moſt illuſtrious manifeſtation of his being the Son of God, in <hi>ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirit of Promiſe.</hi> Acts. XI. 1. <hi>When the day of Pentecoſt was fully come</hi> (Pentecoſt, that is the Fiftieth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152772:24"/> day (there is no reaſon to regard preciſely the Jewiſh Feſtival, or to make a proper name of a common one) on the Fiftieth day, I ſay, which from the Reſurrection muſt needs fall on the Firſt day of the week, reckon it at leiſure) they were all with one accord in one place (continuing ſtill their Aſſemblies on the Firſt day of the week) <hi>and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly there came a ſound from Heaven, as of a mighty wind.</hi> In a word the Holy Spirit moſt miraculouſly came upon them all, as the Lord had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. Here is from our Lord himſelf another ſanctifying of the Lords day to the purpoſe. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, with it, he miraculouſly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified the whole body of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſembled thereon.</p>
            <p>Subſequent hereto, or after the <note place="margin">2. <hi>By his Apoſtles:</hi>
               </note> miſſion of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>the Apoſtles, and Apoſtolical Churches conſtant obſerving the Lords day in its weekly courſe,</hi> as is moſt probable <hi>upon Apoſtolical Orders</hi> for it, was a continued or reinforced practical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution of the ſame. Divine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152772:24"/> I ſaid: For none will doubt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Orders proceeded from the Apoſtles, as Planters of Chriſtianity in the World, were of the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as if they had come imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from Chriſt who ſent them. As to the practice of the Church: <hi>At Troas,</hi> St <hi>Paul</hi> paſſing to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, upon the firſt day of the week, when the Diſciples came together to break Bread preached to them.</hi> Acts xx. 7. St. <hi>Pau'ls</hi> preaching, at that time, might be as to that Church caſual enough: but it appears to have been the ſtated and uſual courſe, the <hi>Dies Natus</hi> for <hi>the Churches meeting together to break Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this ſolemn and continued practice, we have the footſteps of the Apoſtolical mandate it ſelf. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xvi. 1. 2. <hi>Now concerning the collection for the Saints as I have given order to the Churches of Galatia even ſo do yee; upon the firſt day of the Week, let every one of you lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered him, that there be no gathering when I come.</hi> The Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152772:25"/> were of a great extent. He had given orders in thoſe Churches; and now gives orders alſo in <hi>Corinth</hi> for Lords day-alms. The private lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide at home, if we will inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it conſonantly to what we are aſſured to have ſeen from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſual practice, was only in order to the depoſiting all in the Aſſembly, with the Chief Miniſter of the Church, called in <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> days the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Biſhop: For if this had not been deſign'd, the end he mentions would not have been obtained. There would have needed ſtill <hi>a Gathering</hi> of all when he came. But at the celebration of the Euchariſt, ſtyled in thoſe days Breaking of Bread, the Deacons col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, what each perſon offered, and delivered it to the truſt of the Biſhop, as we read more at large in the Antients. This collection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proves a Communion that day, and the Apoſtles order being plain for what was <hi>Acceſſary,</hi> muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for the <hi>Principal.</hi> Now if the Apoſtle gave order for the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152772:25"/> Communion, and Collection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, on the Lords day, no doubt he gave orders for the Aſſemblies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at which the one was to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, and the other made. And then if we admit, that <hi>the Doctrine and Tradition of all the Apoſtles was one and the ſame,</hi> as the Ancients af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, and I know not on what good reaſons any can deny, it will follow, that it was an Apoſtolical Order, that the Lords day ſhould be the day of publick Chriſtan Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>14</label> In this aſſertion of the <hi>ſacredneſs of the Lords Day,</hi> partly from the <note place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are Unanimous herein.</note> Inſtitution of Chriſt and afterwards by the Order of the Apoſtles, <hi>the Antient Fathers are unanimous.</hi> Above all others, memorable is that large Text of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> (an early Martyr of Chriſt, who himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vows, as his Text is commonly rendred, that he ſaw our Lord Jeſus in the fleſh, after his Reſurrection; and who was ordained Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> by the impoſition of the hands of St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf; truely therefore St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, and an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152772:26"/> Apoſtolical Father) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith he. <hi>Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no longer Jewiſhly keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> [that is, neither on the day, nor in the manner the Jews do, which manner he there expoſeth]<hi>—But let each of us ſpiritually keep the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, rejoycing in meditations on the Law of God, admiring the works of his hand—Let every one that loves Chriſt keep the Lords Day—the Queen of days—on which our life roſe, and victory over death was got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:</hi> with more Elogies of it there to be ſeen. Now here the Jewiſh Sabbaths and Sabatiſing are expreſly required to be laid aſide, and a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Reſt, and the Lords Day injoyned inſtead thereof. But St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in his Homily <hi>De Semen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> goes farther and teaches us, <hi>the Lord of the Sabbath</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>tranſlated the Sabbath Day to the Lords Day.</hi> And further: <hi>The Apoſtles &amp; Apoſtolical Men did ordain (namely by our Lords appointment, as in other caſes) that the Lords Day ſhould be kept with Religious Solemnity</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152772:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> And much more on the ſame purpoſe have others which I muſt wave. <hi>Sunday</hi> then does not ſtand on the ſame foot with other Church Holy days. It is <hi>more ſacred,</hi> truly of Divine Right, <hi>the Lords Day,</hi> or a Chriſtian Sabbath.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>15</label> Now as to the true Chriſtian way of keeping it. <hi>I was,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> 
               <note place="margin">How the Lords day is to be kept.</note> 
               <hi>in the Spirit on the Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time will not permit me to preſent the various gloſſes on this phraſe. To ſhorten all: I will readily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, we now adays cannot <hi>be in the ſpirit any Lords day,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> was <hi>on this,</hi> in the Text. He was <hi>in a prophetick extaſy.</hi> But that, which in all likelyhood led him into this exalted temper, and which in our ſtate of things bears analogy thereto, may be and ought to be our entertainment each Lords Day. St. <hi>John</hi> was now <hi>in Patmos,</hi> a ſmall Iſland in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> between <hi>Crete and Aſia minor,</hi> baniſht thither by <hi>Domitian</hi> for the <hi>word of God, and for the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Here was no aſſembly of Chriſtians for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152772:27"/> him to joyn with; But the Lords Day coming upon him in courſe, we cannot well but conceive him taken up in this his Solitude with Prayer, Praiſe, and Contemplations ſuitable to the day; and in theſe being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported, to have had his Soul wholly poſſeſt by the Holy Spirit, and to have received from our Lord all thoſe Revelations, which in this book he Records. And thus paſt that whole day (at leaſt far the greateſt part of it) with the beloved Diſciple. For in one day, as is conceived by very learned Interpreters, had he all thoſe apocalyptick viſions.</p>
            <p>They who cannot aſcend into heaven, may yet go up to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. We are not, in the preſent ſtate, to expect Viſions and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations each Lords Day. St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf had them not, that we know of, but while in <hi>Patmos,</hi> and when God made his Church amends, as I may ſay, for the want of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Miniſtry, by extraordinary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, which were to convince the World and all the Powers of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152772:27"/> Hell, that their malice could not ſuppreſs the Goſpel, but only make it ſhine another way clearer and farther; and that however Tyrants might drive the meſſengers of thoſe glad tydings into deſolate corners, ſo as ſome Aſſemblies might for a ſeaſon want their living voice, yet ſhould they not be able to hinder, but the whole World ſhould ring of their teſtimony wherever they were, and thereby know, in what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and diſguiſes, the Grand Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all the Tyrants on earth (the Devil) has and ſhall, in the ſeveral ages of Mankind, ſet them on work, to the end of all things; ſo that I ſay, St. <hi>Johns</hi> being thus in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was not common even to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Waving then what was extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, Let us attend to what is ordinary and ought to be conſtant. We may, and ought on the Lords Day to be (1) <hi>in Spiritual Exerciſes,</hi> and (2) <hi>in a Spiritual temper</hi> for attending them.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:152772:28"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>16</label> 
               <hi>Spiritual Exerciſes,</hi> I call the offices of Worſhip, or ordinary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <note place="margin">Of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes on the Lords Day.</note> of Devotion on the Lords Day: and thoſe are either <hi>Publick, Private,</hi> or <hi>Secret:</hi> which cannot commonly be omitted without ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publick duties,</hi> are thoſe which are performed in Church Aſſemblies; And they are chiefly four: in their Scripture Names, <hi>Praying, Singing, Doctrine, and Breaking of Bread:</hi> There is no reaſon to ſurmiſe, from what we have extant in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and in the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> that any Lords Day in the Primitive Church paſſed without each of theſe in their Solemnity. What amongſt us is moſt neglected, give me leave to touch upon.</p>
            <p>Of which ſort is <hi>conſtant communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating.</hi> The Chriſtian Church while it continued in any tolerable purity, never ſpent a Lords Day without the Lords Supper; on which of old it was more Scandalous for any Chriſtians to turn their backs, than it is now for Men amongſt us to live Excommunicate: (this I could
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152772:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> eaſily prove at large, but muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear.) And that our own Church eſteems the Lords day but half cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, without the Communion, appears, by her having provided a Communion Service for every Lords Day in the Year. The Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as we have heard, was ever attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Collection for the Poor, now called Oblations. <hi>Never Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt without Offertory.</hi> And this we have ſeen to be as ancient as St. <hi>Pauls</hi> planting the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctrine</hi> was ſubdivided into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying (or Interpreting of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) which we now call Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, into Reading, Exhortation, Teaching, and perhaps otherwiſe. Now the word commonly uſed for teaching is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Catechiſe.</hi> This Office was of ſo great note in the Primitive Church, that it was committed to ſome choice Perſon appointed purpoſely thereto; but him commonly moſt learned. And by Catechiſing I do not mean, meer hearing <hi>young People</hi> repeat the words of their Catechiſm, but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152772:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> expounding to them the Doctrine of it; Examining them upon ſuch Expoſitions, and by all the ſeveral plaineſt ways poſſible, inculcating theſe Doctrines, till they underſtand them. And for gaining reverence to this Office, as well as for other reaſons, which I will not name, <hi>Elder people ought to fit by.</hi> In a word all forrein Churches outdo us herein: And if we take not more care, than yet uſual amongſt us as to this work, we ſhall without a miracle, in the next age, go very neer to looſe our Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Private Duties</hi> I call thoſe which are performed in private Families; Parents, Children, Sojourners, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, joyning in Prayer and Praiſes to God, and in reading his Word, and other good Books as conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency offers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secret Duties</hi> are ſuch as every Chriſtian ſhould perform by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Cloſet or Retirements Such are Meditation, ſelf Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Recollection of our improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in the cloſe, Prayer and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152772:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> Thankſgiving as occaſion requires.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Section </seg>XVII</label> Thoſe who demand <hi>Proof</hi> for theſe, being duties of the day, will give me leave to ask them whether <note place="margin">Proof for theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> ſuch practices in the Family, or in the Cloſet, be neceſſary, and duties on any day? If they be ſo, there is no ſufficient reaſon for their omiſſion on the Lords day, when by Law of God and Man there is moſt leiſure for them. Beſides they will be pleaſed to conſult <hi>Numbers</hi> xxviii. 9, 10. where they will find the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar <hi>ſacrifice for the Sabbath, both Morning and Evening,</hi> was required of the Jews, over and above the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual daily Burnt offering;</hi> the like too upon the New Moons, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. and on other Feſtivals, <hi>ver. ult.</hi> That which I infer from hence is, that the publick Lords Days Worſhip, and other Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Offices, muſt not ſupercede or abate our ordinary Private or Secret Devotions on thoſe Dayes. Theſe are to be faithfully ſuperaded to them.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152772:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Section </seg>XVIII</label> This haply ſome will cry out is <hi>Fanaticiſm, Puritaniſm, Sabbatari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm,</hi> and the like. <note place="margin">A Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Practice from ill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, there may be a Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal (and perhaps a Phariſaical) way too of doing theſe duties; but the practice of the duties it ſelf is not Fanatical or Phariſaical; and much leſs is it Sabbatarianiſm. We muſt make Fanaticks and Sabbatarians of the moſt Ancient Fathers of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, and the moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctors and Pillars of our own Church, if we can find either Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticiſme or Sabbatarianiſme in ſpending the whole Lords day in a ſucceſſion, or holy exchange of ſuch Duties, as theſe mentioned. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> was no Fanatick nor Sabbata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, yet in his ſecond Apology he tells us the Chriſtians of that age, which was but one hundred and forty Years from Chriſt, <hi>uſed to repeat at home what they had learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that day in the Publick Aſſembly. Origen</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> were no Fanaticks, nor yet Sabbatarians, yet both (nay the later more than once)
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152772:30"/> preſs the ſpending (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c.) <hi>This whole day in the exerciſe of Spirituals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to wave others of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents and come neerer home. I ſcarce think any Son of the preſent Church will adventure to brand the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Sixths</hi> days with Fanaticiſim or Sabbatarianiſm: yet under that, I find a <hi>Canon</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for <hi>ſpending the Lords Day in private Prayer and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, acknowledging our Offences, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling our ſelves to our Brethren, viſiting the Sick, comforting the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, relieving the Poor, and inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children and Servants in the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and fear of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to be ſure, the Authors of the <hi>Book of Homilies</hi> we muſt not ſay were either Fanaticks or Sabbata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians: For the Homilies we are bound ſtill to ſubſcribe and approve at leaſt, if not publickly to read: yet they teach, that <hi>on this day people ſhauld ceaſe from all common and bodily labour and give themſelves Wholly</hi> [note that word] <hi>to the</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152772:31"/> 
               <hi>exerciſes of Gods true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Arch Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> againſt the <hi>Admonitioners,</hi> was no Fanatick, Puritan, or Sabbatarian, yet ſaith he; <hi>no man doubteth the meaning of theſe words, Six days ſhalt thou labour,</hi> &amp;c. to be this, <hi>that ſeing God hath permitted us Six days to do our own works in, we ought in the Seventh Wholly to ſerve him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Francis White,</hi> in his Book againſt the Sabbatarians, was neither Fanatick nor Sabbatarian, yet he tells us our Church requires, that <hi>upon the Lords day Parents and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, inſtruct their Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the fear and nurture of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> was neither Fanatick nor Sabbatarian, yet he teaches, <hi>we are to account the Sanctification of one Whole day in the week, a Duty which Gods immutable Law doth enact for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, I believe no ſober man will ſay that Excellent Book, <hi>The Whole duty of man,</hi> ſavours either of Fanaticiſm or Sabbatarianiſm, yet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152772:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Partit:</hi> 2. Sect. 17. The Author teaches all in their Families the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice I have perſwaded.</p>
            <p>But will ſome ſay, there were in our Church who have taught other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, who have juſtified Sports and Revels on this day. Yes, and there are too many at preſent who pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice otherwiſe; but I fear not to ſay, both the one and the other, were and are (I will hope not intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, yet in reality and effect) in this part the depravers of Religion, the corrupters and diſturbers of our Church. It were eaſy to take off that thin vail of learning, with which ſuch liberties have been ſet off; but I muſt not divert thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Section </seg>XIX</label> A word I ought to ſpeak to that temper of mind, with which we are to attend holy duties; which ought <note place="margin">Of ſpiritual Temper.</note> indeed to poſſeſs us every day, but more eſpecially on the Lords day. That I called a <hi>ſpiritual temper.</hi> The term I ground on thoſe Texts. <hi>Jude</hi> 26. <hi>Praying in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 6. 18. <hi>Praying always with all manner of Prayer and Supplication</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152772:32"/> 
               <hi>in the Spirit:</hi> by which term, <hi>Spirit,</hi> no doubt both the Apoſtles meant, not praying with any ſuch imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſpiritual gift of Prayer, as is cryed up for abſolutely neceſſary by many, but <hi>praying with a devout holy temper of mind;</hi> a temper conſiſting in the union of thoſe ſeveral Graces of Gods Spirit, which ought to be exerciſed in Prayer: In ſhort, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a heart full of Faith, and of Love towards God and Mankind; of the hopes of Glory, and ſo of contempt of this World. I may not now take time farther to open this Temper: but with ſuch temper as this, ſhould we this day perform all thoſe parts of worſhip, which we<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any where offer. And to be employ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed in prayer and praiſe, and in like offices mentioned, with ſuch temper, is to be as much <hi>in the Spirit on the Lords Day,</hi> as in the preſent ſtate of things, we can be. But I muſt draw to a concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect </seg>XX</label> You have heard, beloved, how the antient Chriſtians kept the <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> Lords Day, and how we may and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152772:32"/> ought to ſpend ours: Now give me leave to ask you (or will you be pleaſed to ask your ſelves) how you ſpend yours?</p>
            <p>In the Morning, if you can, many <note place="margin">By way of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</note> of you dreſs your ſelves more Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Phantaſtically, than you do all the Week; that's your firſt labour: Then ſome of you get a better Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt than on other days. Then to Church, and ſhew your ſelves; where if you are a little demure in part of the Prayers, that's the ſumm total of your Devotion. At other times you Gaze, one while you Whiſper, Talk and Laugh; another while ſome compoſe themſelves, and Sleep. How ſmall is the conſtantly-Serious, Devout and attentive Part? How ſtrange a body now now adays is a Chriſtian Aſſembly? Then, when the Morning Offices are done, a more liberal Dinner than on other days, and what diverſion we can find within doors, or without, as the weather ſerves, entertains the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of us, the reſt of the day. Good Lord forgive, Good Lord amend this.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:152772:33"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Wherefore,</hi> In a word, let what has <note place="margin">By way of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſion.</note> been ſaid prevail with all for a more reverend eſteem &amp; ſtrict obſervation of the Lords Day: Let us diſtinguiſh it from other days, by ſomething elſe, than Holy-day Cloaths and Holy day Fare, and Holy-day Liberties. I muſt ſtand to it; the keeping up, amongſt us, not only that ſmall remain of the power of Godlineſs, which is yet left, but the very face of the Reformed Religion (which God be bleſſed we have fairer than our neighbours) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends very much hereon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Works of mercy</hi> may be, and ought <note place="margin">By way of Caution.</note> to be done on this day, as well as on any other. When they come from a pious heart, they are Acts of Devotion, in his eſteem, who hath ſaid, <hi>I will have mercy and not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> And <hi>works of neceſſity,</hi> or <hi>grand conveniency,</hi> ſuch as ſecuring neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of life when periſhing, dreſſing fit food, or the like, foraſmuch as they are neer a-kin to works of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, are not on this day unlawful to Chriſtian People. St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in the place before mentioned, taxes
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152772:33"/> the <hi>feeding on cold Meat, this day,</hi> as a point of <hi>Judaizing.</hi> And there is an antient Canon, amongſt thoſe called Apoſtolical, <hi>againſt faſting on the Lords Day.</hi> Wherefore certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch refreſhment of our Bodies, and regard to their vigour, as may keep up our Spirits in the ſervice of God, is not to be neglected. We ought this day, if any day, <hi>to eat our meat with gladneſs,</hi> as well as <hi>ſingleneſs of heart.</hi> But in all theſe things, we muſt be faithful to God and our ſelves; not framing neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of buſineſs where there are none, and taking care, we in ſuch ſort uſe not the ſuccours of Nature, as to turn them into burdens and hindran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>I have done, and beſeech God, what I have thus plainly, though too precipitantly, and briefly ſaid, may effect in all, or ſome of us at leaſt, a more conſtant, conſcientious and ſpiritual diſcharge of our <hi>Publick, Private</hi> and <hi>Secret duties</hi> on this day. By this means a vein of intelligent and ſerious Religion will ſoon run
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152772:34"/> through Families, and, by them, through Pariſhes, through City and Country. And this will ſoon ſettle and ſecure Religion to us; and Religion ſettled will certainly ſettle and ſecure the Nation; At leaſt, if God ſee not fit to ſettle any of us here in this World, it will prepare and lead ſuch of us, who are ſpiritual Worſhippers of him, to an eternal ſettlement; to a better Country, and therein to that glorious <hi>Sabbatiſm which remains for the Children of God.</hi> To which our Heavenly Father bring us all through Chriſt Jeſus. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152772:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
